Guide to the Alfred M. and Clarisse B. Hellman Collection
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Alfred M. and Clarisse B. Hellman Collection,
[ca. 1850]-1952
ca. 400 items (14 boxes, 1 oversized folder)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4078881
Biographical Note
Scope and Content
The collection of D.H. Lawrence material contains two book-length manuscripts, the typescripts of Sea and Sardinia and The Boy in the Bush, both with manuscript corrections in Lawrence's hand. The typescript for The Boy In The Bush is probably the manuscript from which the book was printed. Other Lawrence manuscripts include "The Future of the Novel," and Chapter 13 of Aaron's Rod. Correspondents include Thomas Seltzer, Johathan Cape, Mrs. Nancy Henry, and Lady Ottoline Morrell. The collection also contains three watercolor drawings made by Lawrence for the jacket of the English edition of The Plumed Serpent. Related printed material is also included. The John Steinbeck material is comprised of one letter, and proofs for thirteen of Steinbeck's works, including East Of Eden and Of Mice and Men. Also included are a printed biography and photographs, and printed ephemera relating to many of Steinbeck's works. There are books inscribed to Alfred and Clarisse Hellman. This collection also contains some correspondence of Alfred Hellman and some letters collected by Dr. Morton Pepper.
Subjects
Lawrence, D. H. (David Herbert), 1885-1930.; Steinbeck, John, 1902-1968.; Seltzer, Thomas.; Cape, Jonathan, 1879-1960.; Henry, Nancy.; Morrell, Ottoline Violet Anne Cavendish-Bentinck, Lady, 1873-1938.; Hellman, Alfred M.; Hellman, Clarisse B.; Pepper, Morton.; American literature--20th century.; English literature--20th century.; Authors, English.; Authors, American.; Literature publishing.; Drawings.
Access Restrictions
Reader must use microfilm of The Boy in the Bush.
Acquisition
1968 M-68 Hellman, Clarisse B. Gift
Alternate Formats
Microfilm available.
- Series I: Correspondence and Miscellaneous
  - Lowell, James Russell to Robert Browning, 5 November 1882 (Box 1)
  - Dewey, George. Summary statement of receipts and expenditures, filled out and signed by Paymaster E.B. Rogers, OK’d by J.D. Robnett; forwarded to and approved by Admiral Dewey, with his signature. (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous: Saks & Company sales receipt; Woodrow Wilson post card; B. Altman receipt; Bloomingdale Bros. receipt. (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, (2 Folders) (Box 1)
- Series II: D.H. Lawrence Material
  - Lawrence, D.H.: (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous printed material (1 Folder) (Box 2)
    - Editorials and reviews (1 Folder) (Box 2)
    - Paperbacks, etc. (Box 2)
  - Lawrence, D.H.: (Box 3)
    - Related printed material – 2 criticism (Box 3)
  - Lawrence, D.H.: (Box 4)
    - Related printed material – 3 criticism (Box 4)
  - Lawrence, D.H.: (Box 5)
    - Related printed material – 4 Anthologies (Box 5)
  - D.H. Lawrence: (Box 6)
    - Related printed material – 5 Anthologies (Box 6)
- Series III: John Steinbeck Material
  - Steinbeck, John: (Box 7)
    - Autograph letter to George Joel, September 1938 (1 Folder) (Box 7)
    - Cannery Row. Unrevised galley proof, 59 p. 1945 (1 Folder) (Box 7)
    - Bombs Away. Unrevised galley proof, 86 p. 1942 (1 Folder) (Box 7)
    - The Long Valley. Advance reader’s copy, 146 p. 1938 (1 Folder) (Box 7)
    - The Moon is Down. Galley proofs, 37 p., 1942 (1 Folder) (Box 7)
    - In the Forests of the Night. Unrevised galley proof, 73 p. 1950 (1 Folder) (Box 7)
    - East of Eden. Unrevised galley proof, 465 p. 1952 (1 Folder) (Box 7)
    - Of Mice and Men. Galley proof, 41p. 1937 (1 Folder) (Box 8)
    - The Pearl. Unrevised galley proof, 71 p. 1947 (1 Folder) (Box 8)
    - A Russian Journal. Unrevised galley proof, 112 p. 1948 (1 Folder) (Box 8)
    - A Russian Journal. Proofs of photographs by Robert Capa, 68 photographs 1948 (1 Folder) (Box 8)
    - Sea of Cortez. Unrevised galley proof, 159 p. 1941 (1 Folder) (Box 8)
    - Sea of Cortez. Advance proof copy, 277 p. 1941 (1 Folder) (Box 8)
    - The Wayward Bus. Unrevised galley proof, 176 p. 1947 (1 Folder) (Box 8)
  - Steinbeck, John: (Box 9)
    - Pictures (1 Folder) (Box 9)
    - Short stories in various magazines (1 Folder) (Box 9)
    - Biography and criticism (1 Folder) (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous printed articles (1 Folder) (Box 9)
    - Articles from England, June-December 1943 (1 Folder) (Box 9)
    - Burning Bright (Books of The Times) (1 Folder) (Box 9)
    - East of Eden (Books of The Times), etc. (1 Folder) (Box 9)
    - The Forgotten Village. Program (1 Folder) (Box 9)
    - The Grapes of Wrath. Printed ephemera (1 Folder) (Box 9)
    - In Dubious Battle. Printed ephemera (1 Folder) (Box 9)
    - The Moon is Down. Printed ephemera (1 Folder) (Box 9)
    - Of Mice and Men. Printed ephemera (1 Folder) (Box 9)
    - A Russian. Journal. Printed ephemera (1 Folder) (Box 9)
    - Sea of Cortez. Printed ephemera (1 Folder) (Box 9)
    - Tortilla Flat. Printed ephemera (1 Folder) (Box 9)
    - The Wayward Bus. Printed ephemera (1 Folder) (Box 9)
- Series IV: Inscribed Books and Photograph
  - Books inscribed to Alfred and Clarisse Hellman (Box 10-12)
  - Photograph of Alfred Hellman